<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation anent elders of kirk sessions, 1684</title>
            <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183363</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299264</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299264</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05494)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2810:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation anent elders of kirk sessions, 1684</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>Scotland Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Title vignette: royal seal with initials C R.</note>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Intentional blank spaces in text.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: dark, crease with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ecclesiastical law --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:179998:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="6 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure> 
               <add>James by the grace of god</add>
            </head>
            <head>A PROCLAMATION Anent Elders of Kirk Seſsions, 1684.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES, by the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>Great-Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith;</signed>
               <salute>To Our Lovits,  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap> Macers of Our Privy Council, Meſſengers at Arms, Our Sheriffs in that part, conjunctly and ſeverally, ſpecially conſtitute, Greeting:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Foraſmuch as by the Supremacy Inherent in Our Imperial Crown, as one of the Prerogatives thereto belonging; It ſolely Reſides in Us, to Enact and Emit ſuch Conſtitutions, Acts and Orders, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Adminiſtration of the External Government of the Church, and the Perſons to be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed therein, as We, in Our Royal Wiſdom ſhall think fit, <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="5+ letters">
                  <desc>•••••…</desc>
               </gap>ly ſpecified in the firſt <hi>Act</hi> of Our ſecond <hi>Parliament:</hi> And therefore We, and Our Predeceſſors, have always been careful that the Diſcipline of the Church, by Kirk Seſſions and otherwayes be obſerved; for preſervation whereof, it being neceſſar, that Perſons of good Reputation, and known Loyalty, ſhould aſſiſt the Miniſters in the exerciſe of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Diſcipline. We therefore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with Advice of the Lords of Our Privy Council, Do hereby Impower the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the reſpective Parochs, within this Our ancient Kingdom, to give in Liſts to the Biſhops, their Ordinaries, of ſuch as are fit to Serve as Elders in the ſaids Parochs, and being approven by them; We hereby Ordain and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Perſons ſo Named and Authorized, to Serve as Elders, except they can offer ſuch ſufficient Reaſons, to be allowed by the Biſhop, as may excuſe them from Serving in the ſaid Imployment, with Certification to the Perſons who ſhall refuſe, not being lawfully excuſed, as ſaid is, that upon production of the ſaid Nomination, and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments taken upon their refuſal, Letters of Horning ſhall be direct, under the Signet of Our Privy Council, Charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to accept and Officiate, within fifteen Dayes, under the pain of Rebellion: And to the effect, Our Pleaſure in the Premiſſes may be made known, to all Perſons concerned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Our Will is, and We Charge you ſtrictly and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that incontinent, theſe Our Letters ſeen, ye paſs to the Mercat Croſs of <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> and remanent Mercat Croſſes of the head Burghs of the Shires of this Kingdom, and other places needful, and there, by open Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, make publication of the Premiſſes, that all Perſons concerned may give obedience thereto, according to Juſtice, as ye will anſwer to Us thereupon, the which to do, we commit to you, conjunctly and ſeverally, Our full power, by thir Our Letters, delivering them by you, duely execute, and indorſed again to the Bearer.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under Our Signet at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 
                  <date>the twenty two day of <hi>April,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred eighty and four. And of Our Reign, the thirtieth ſixth Year. 1684.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Per actum Dominorum Secreti Concilij. <hi>WILL. PATERSON,</hi> Cls. Sti. Concilij.</signed>
               <lb/>
GOD ſave the KING.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to His moſt Sacred Majeſty, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
